[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
everyone welcome to the stoa i'm peter
limberg the steward of the stoa
stow is a place for us to cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
nice edge of this very
moment and today we have jillian
richardson
uh the author of and she's waving right
there in case you want to
determine who that is and then she's
author of the unlonely planet
how healthy congregations can change the
world and she's the founder of something
called
the joy list which has a mission to make
new york city and probably the world at
this point uh
a less lonely place
and it's just a very timely kind of uh
you know moment to have jillian on
because we've been talking about
loneliness a lot here
at the stoa and we're sort of doing what
she's writing about
uh and doing in in herself in new york
is just kind of ameliorating loneliness
through building community or
what uh us cool medicines like to call
communitas
um so what we're going to do today is uh
jillian adam have a conversation for
about you know 10 15 minutes
and if you have any uh questions
throughout just start throwing them in
the chat right now
i'll call on you and mute yourself ask
your question to jillian um
if you liked it me to read it on your
behalf because we'll go on youtube just
indicate that in the chats and then i'll
read on your behalf
so i think that's everything um i'll
allow
everyone to unmute themselves uh so
welcome
to the store julian
so much for having me i'm really excited
to be here and as i was just saying to
you i'm so curious about all of you in
this community as well
that's just how my brain works so i'm
excited to
to drop in and see what all this is
about beautiful
yeah and feel free to ask us any
questions that come alive for you as
well
um you asked me a difficult one before
we let people in i
didn't have an answer so i was trying to
get around it um
yeah so is there anything maybe uh for
people coming in who don't know
uh anything about your work or your book
is there anything you would like to
frame
the conversation before i start asking
uh more specific
questions yeah i think i'll just say
kind of the the biggest question that
people ask me
when like i'm at a party or something
and they're like oh what do you do
i give them one of two answers i either
say i study loneliness
or i say i help people make friends like
those are kind of the two
options and then they typically ask
why and
it's just because it's the thing that
i've struggled with the most in my life
and it's it's kind of like what you
would call the the wounded healer
like the places where i felt the most
pain in my own life is where
i feel the most qualified to help people
with what they're struggling with
and really when i moved to new york city
after college
didn't really know anyone i i had this
moment where like i kind of knew one guy
in the city
and we were gonna go out and i was all
excited like my first
night as an adult in new york city
and he totally ghosted on me and i had
no one to hang out with
and just the feeling in my body in that
moment of
i'm alone here i have no support i don't
know
people was terrifying
and i kind of vowed to myself i wasn't
gonna
let anyone make me feel that way again
like make me feel that way again
and just dedicated a year of my life to
really finding who my people are because
i realize
i never really felt at home in a group
of friends
and like the people around me lifted me
up and helped me become a better version
of me
i i was a comedy kid in college
and so is like in the sketch comedy
improv world
was like the president of my school's
improv group
and looking back i realized we were all
kind of using
humor as a way to denigrate ourselves
and kind of
take each other down a notch and
it wasn't very kind and i wanted to find
people
who who were kinder than that and when i
started to find those spaces
intersected with when donald trump was
elected
in and so my newsletter actually started
november and 2016
because there was a juxtaposition of
feeling like for me things were hopeless
i heard my friends saying things like
people are bad
i can't trust anyone anymore like
things are hopeless that kind of thing
with
at the same time being around the most
loving inspiring people i'd ever met
and i wanted to let people know that in
new york city
every day of the week there's these
beautiful spaces where you can go and be
in community and connection
and what happened then and then i'll
i'll wrap up my story is
that people started coming up to me
once i released this newsletter and
being like
thank you for sharing how lonely you
felt i feel that way and i thought i was
the only one
i didn't know other people felt that way
i started getting emails from strangers
who didn't even live in new york city
like i just got divorced and i'm with my
kids and i don't know how to meet people
and like
you you've given voice to my experience
and
the more i learned and as i decided to
write a book on loneliness
that it's such a common human experience
that we feel such
deep shame around and that we really
just need to talk about it and voice it
and
share how we can step out of our own
loneliness if we want to
because sometimes loneliness can be a
really beautiful powerful feeling
um and that's that's my whole deal
that's that's what i've dedicated my
life to is just creating
community and connection because we we
really
really need it especially right now
so that's who i am hi um
yeah there's just so many threads that i
want to take you down um
where do you think that shame comes from
um i mean so for me and this is a thing
i've
discussed discussed very publicly but i
come from a
pretty dysfunctional family and if
you've been in any sort of 12-step
group or sitting in the in the chat me
too we're like
yeah when we really look at it most of
us come from dysfunctional families a
lot of people just don't
talk about it um but the kind of the
three rules of a dysfunctional family is
don't talk don't trust don't feel
like don't talk don't trust don't feel
those are kind of the three pillars
and so for me since feeling disconnected
is tied with sadness it's tied
with kind of like maybe anger
like these feelings that are not
acceptable in a lot of households to
talk about you kind of just
shove that down and put on a smile be a
good girl everything's okay
there's there's there's nothing but
pleasantness in here
uh i think that's where the shame comes
from
and i'm curious um for whatever reason
that
the question of a gender divide came up
to mind when i was reading some of your
stuff
do you think women experience loneliness
in a different way than men do
i okay i'm just gonna answer this off
the cuff
um this isn't something i've actually
talked about very much but what just
immediately popped to the top of my mind
was that in my experience of working
with women
um the loneliness can come from not
feeling like their emotional selves are
fully expressed
that in my own experience it was
realizing i had no place to express rage
or
grief or like these deep emotions that
make up part of who i
am that there were not safe spaces for
me to
to share those feelings and so i as a
person did not feel fully expressed
and i'm actually i'm in a women's group
now where that is the point is to be
able to
it's kind of like community therapy with
each other where we're always expressing
these things that
socially we're told to not express a lot
of the time
and with men i think that is also true
of your full emotional self isn't
expressed there's
maybe a little different flavor of like
i know
with a lot of guys there's there's a
difficult time with even asking men to
hang out in the first place
and really this is just the thing with
people but this is what i've heard from
women i've worked with
they'll say something along the lines of
like can you just tell my husband that
it's okay to ask a guy to go get tacos
with him
like that there's a block of even asking
guys to hang out with you in the first
place
um in very broad strokes and also i'm
seeing in the comments grown men don't
cry
this is um i'm i call myself like the
number one lady advocate of men's work
like i refer men to men's circles and
men's groups
so often because i see what
happens when men do not have the support
of emotionally mature men
like that's where so much physical and
emotional violence comes from is when
these healing or these um these patterns
of abuse are not broken
and so with men
uh for for the people who are male
identifying in the room
i super recommend a documentary called
the work
which is by my friend gethin aldis so
good that documentary know it
yeah i watched it well have you talked
about it in this group before
not yet not yet okay uh just quickly
it is about a men's group inside of
folsom prison
where it's half men from outside of
prison half men
in prison uh and oh
the documentarian is a man named gethin
aldis
uh who also he lives in new york city
and
it's the one time of year where these
prisoners
get a space to express what's going on
with them emotionally
and the prisoners are actually um or
like the men who are in prison
are kind of the mentor figures for the
men from outside of prison
and it's a really really painful but
gorgeous
depiction of how
much emotional gunk
people are holding inside and what
happens when you're in a space where you
really can just let it rip
like it's gut wrenching like it's a very
intense documentary to watch
and at the same time it's just so moving
to see like wow when these men trust
each other and support each other look
at what they can do
like it's more work than you could do in
years with a therapist because
at least in my opinion it's healing done
in community with other men
and the same applies to women when you
know that you can trust women
and you can show these things that's
more than you can just do with one
person like it's a whole different type
of healing
yeah yeah and then that's what i echo
those thoughts of that documentary is
really good um
and so i've done a lot of like that
similar encounter work and somatic stuff
and kind of psychotherapeutic work and i
feel like i can
have good homosocial relationships with
men and
but i i do think i've never heard that
before it's not my turn but it's a
technical
uh meta term uh but um
i i do think there's like a uh what they
call man box you know with male homo
social relationships where you can't
show weakness you can't show this
which is a barrier which engenders
loneliness um
but one thing that i'm getting to
realize that a lot of women have
trouble making friends with other women
like my wife is jealous of my male
friends and how we can just bond
and then talk in like kind of a free
associative way and
there seems to be barriers there so i'm
just want to double click on that
uh if there's any truth or any resonance
there in that statement
i like that i want to double click on it
um this is why i love joining different
communities because i get to hear like
the lingo that's totally common for
everyone and then i'm like i've
literally never heard someone say that
in my life so cool
i should apologize in advance before
there's so much lingo that you're
walking into
it's so cool um
i think it can definitely be true and
like the the women's group that i'm a
part of is called woman within and we
have
kind of the initiation into your women's
circle which is every week or every
other week is a weekend
long experience that i super recommend
for
post covent times um
but a gift of that is being able to hear
the struggles of a lot of different
types of women and a lot of different
stages in their lives
and i think like i
hearing a woman so openly just say
i don't think i can trust other women
like
i i don't trust other women and
it wasn't a thought i had ever
consciously had and yet because of
experiences
like with with my sister with my mother
realizing that's it's definitely there
it's not a thought i've i've consciously
thought before
there there's a really great book uh
i love that this is a space where it
feels like i can just go super deep and
nerdy on this
uh there's a book called the heroine's
journey
which i really recommend for anyone
who's female identifying
and also considers yourself kind of like
a father's daughter
like someone who you really want to
please
your dad like there's a lot of uh like
you're his star you're his golden
child which is totally me
uh and it really sheds a
painful uncomfortable amount of light on
like
why you might have perfectionist
tendencies why you might gravitate
more towards male friends than female
friends
and like the the healing cycle of that
it's gorgeous and
also totally not a light read so
warning on that but it's really powerful
that's cool um should be a stolen
session
uh that that journey so cool because
it's she's arguing that the hero's
journey is different than the heroine's
journey like the hero's journey is much
more
masculine like there's a goal and you
get to it and it's over and the
heroine's journey is much more cyclical
like a death and rebirth cycle
and it's a really great look at like oh
wow this
story structure that we just sew or i so
just felt was true
like that's what it is there's a
completely different way of looking at
it
it's more feminine leaning you'll see
someone in the comments being like over
and over
it keeps going forever right
so something else i wanted to um circle
back to
when you mention your improv i think
your acting uh experience
and it's funny because keith johnstone
kind of the pioneer of improv is coming
in tomorrow uh
to at the stoa to do um a talk and i
spoke with them on the phone
uh last week and i have an improv
background as well and i didn't really
vibe with
i loved improv but i didn't vibe with
the people in improv because when you
hang out with them for beer it's just
like they're just
competing each other with jokes you know
it's like can we just have like a real
conversation it's like they gotta say
something i think i see something funny
and then the um that the whole kind of
the sketch mentality because you're kind
of
hunting for the laugh and then you get
kind of like it's like a super normal
stimuli you get addicted to
it and then you just kind of mold your
character around that and uh
it's funny that keith was say it again
it's sort of like um a display or some
kind of
device that captures an evolutionary
adaptive thing and then heightens it so
like porn is a super normal stimuli
for example or laugh tracks and comedy
shows as a super normal stimuli
and uh anyway so keith johnson was was
like
making fun of this too but i was like on
the phone which is quite awesome uh
and so what i mentioned that is that
there seems to be like a narcissistic
component there it's like pointing the
finger back on me
when you're doing that and that's sort
of like anti-community
uh so i'm curious if you can tease out
some of the characteristics between
these sort of anti-communities
and what you're cultivating their uh uh
with actual community
yeah well i mean even
for me someone who wrote a
book about community
there's just so many individualistic
tendencies in me
because of the culture i was raised in
like living in america
that it's still
very counter-intuitive for me to
act in community like it's such a muscle
and i feel like that muscle for me has
so deteriorated during this time of
covid
um because i i tend to like to build
community by connecting people
and creating gatherings in person
and i don't really get to do that right
now
as much um there's there's a postcard on
my fridge that i'm looking at
that a friend sent me that says how to
build community and then it's like this
list
of things and it's just
so many actions that people don't
do like talking to your neighbor making
food and giving people in your community
extra like working in a community garden
just like
lists of things like that it's probably
like 50 things
and it's really
tragic that we live in a culture
where there's so much hustle and grind
that
i was about to say being able to
contribute to your community is a luxury
i don't think that's actually true i
think it more feels like a luxury like
oh if i had more time i would totally
make brownies and gifts up to my
neighbors or like whatever
um i wish i had a better understanding
of like
capitalism and its impact on
individualism because i would have
incorporated it more into my book
but that's just not my expertise so much
and and so when it comes to like the the
practical aspects uh
like with the joy list and the things
that you're doing so how what are what
are the steps you have taken and then
are you
taking to build community development
well it's funny because
i'm so aware of the irony of everything
that i do
that my newsletter is to help people
find their community i would not argue
that my newsletter is a community
whatsoever
like it is me telling other people where
they can go
to find their community uh i would not
say that my newsletter is a community
like if someone told me that my
newsletter was their community i would
feel
concerned because it's just one woman
sending a bunch of people an email every
week like it's not even very interactive
um i used to have in-person events
called the joyless social where it was
the whole point was you come to this
event alone
so you can meet other people in new york
city who want to make friends
and it's like such a sweet space and i
miss it
uh and i would think that was more of a
community
because if there is a volunteer there's
a bunch of volunteers there's a
volunteer coordinator
there's people who show up every time
there's people who want to contribute
like there's musicians who come
and even then it's like it's still a
thing that if i didn't
make it happen it wouldn't happen
uh and so i struggle with that
of hoping that people
find their their network of friends
while also realizing the thing that i am
offering is not really
in alignment with those values so much
and what i'm getting is you're like a a
community matchmaker
like instead of matching people you're
matchmaking communities together forming
them
yeah this guy sent me an email yesterday
where he was like
what did he say he said um he's like i
refer to you as community goddess
like you're the person who like brings
people to where they need to go
but you're not the like you're not the
community
which i'll totally take that title
and uh so the last question i'll have
then we can pivot to the chats and feel
free to ask us any um any questions as
well
uh this is kind of related to store two
um
since kovit came along this is the title
i think i'll actually talk community
coved what is your sense of online
communities forming
and how are they different from
in-person communities
well it's really interesting because i
so i have a bias
of being someone who's more of an
ambivert like i
i do get energy from people but only a
very specific type of person and i need
to be
alone to recharge uh you'd probably
assume i'm the most extroverted person
in the history of the planet
uh but i
i have a newsletter with a curated type
of event because i'm only energized by a
certain type of space
like if you drop me into a networking
event with no facilitation like i'll
want to die
and run away um i see it laura's like
yes
totally relate to that um
and but at the same time i'm not
completely introverted
and so that's a bias that i have that i
need to remember
and i've heard from people who've been
organizing very consistent online spaces
that they've actually had more people
show up than they've ever had at their
in-person events
and people are more engaged and i think
part of that is because
since we're behind our computer screens
and if i wanted to i could just
literally close my laptop and all of you
disappear
potentially depending on my personality
i could be more vulnerable more present
more open with all of you here
than i could be at an in-person
gathering
and that that's actually an unexpected
gift for a lot of community leaders to
see like
people are even more invested there's
more types of people showing up
than ever before my church is actually
the same way more people are
like attending services online
than they did in person and so that's
also
an interesting thing to consider and so
i i notice people who are in the
community space are
so it's so easy to just [ __ ] on virtual
gatherings
when there are some really beautiful
positives to them at the same time
yeah i feel like um
you know since i launched a store since
the covet came online like about over
six months ago now um
like i my network
through net playing really has increased
tenfold uh
and it's like you know you throw that
strange attractor out there and then or
that beacon
and then you find the others all over
the world that i wouldn't otherwise find
if i was just localized
to toronto so it's very um
very exciting
all right so uh ready to pivot to some
questions in the
the chats okay
uh karen or kieran you you're next
figure up
[Music]
just are you are you getting um like a
darth vader
kind of muffled voice okay cool
yeah your audio is really weird it's
like yeah you sound like darth vader
it's kind of cool though
how about now oh you're good now yeah
okay
oh if i could control the dark
brotherness that'd be amazing
um okay now i was just going to say i'll
read what i just have
in the in the chat and doing to what
extent are
the duration and the intensity of a
shared experience
important for developing that sense of
belonging because you can meet somebody
for five minutes every week but it's not
the same as maybe just going through
something
with somebody and i wonder what your
experience of that is with the events
that you
most are helping
thank you for that question so i'm
hearing the questions kind of like what
how does the duration intensity of an
event impact your sense of belonging
is that right yeah well thinking on my
my own life i feel like
they're in my book i talk about there's
this event i went to called camp
grounded
which is a four-day digital detox
summer camp for adults so it's like no
technology
uh it's a sober space you use like a
silly name
instead of your real name my name was
lady
uh and even though it was only
four days the experience
completely shifted my perception of what
was possible in terms of relating
because it was the first space i'd ever
been in where
like it was it was first of all curated
so much to be like
to show up here you have to be the type
of adult who is willing to
not talk about work use a silly name be
sober
not have your phone with a bunch of
people in the woods
and so that was kind of a gate already
and to see like these are adults who are
so
open so playful and i
bonded with these people in four days
more than i had bonded with friends in
my entire life
like no joke and
so on the one hand that's so beautiful
because it was such a short amount of
time and such an intensity of belonging
and bonding and yet at the same time
because there wasn't
a um like some sort of campgrounded
event series outside of the space
the the friendships start to
dwindle a little bit over time if
there's not
something that an organizer is putting
together
and so i wish sometimes like i see these
gorgeous retreats that people host where
like people
bond and they're opening their hearts
and it's like incredible
and then cut to a year later and those
people aren't talking anymore because
nothing has been organized to bring them
together again
uh and i wish that more people did that
because
especially retreats were very like
you're really vulnerable
like i've been in retreats where it's
like our souls just got busted open
and now we're just back
in our lives with like no form of coming
back together
or checking in with each other uh it
feels almost irresponsible a little bit
so i wish people did a better job of
that
i hope that answers your question
do you have any follow-up also i'm
curious if you're in ireland
well i i am irish but i'm not in ireland
at the moment though
cool my mom is irish so just hearing
your voice makes me feel excited
um no in terms of following just to say
that i find something similar that
follow-up stuff
is is so important because i almost feel
like an event can crash
things together and then it's about just
maintaining it and recently
some chats with friends have been the
idea that you can actually be friends
with almost anybody
because the friendship thing is almost
just we've been through stuff
together so you don't need to meet you
don't have to have shared interest you
just need to have shared kind of
homeless memories and my best friends
are the longest ones not necessarily
the most intense events or anything like
that and the follow-up is something
that really helps with that personally
so yeah cool thank you
cool thank you all right dan
feldman you had a question
yes i had a question um i was wondering
if you could
share your um your opinions and your
feelings on what
what you believe the difference between
an american
like american-style meetups based around
mutual interest for example you know the
bowling alone idea
bowling together in the in the 50s and
that sort of thing
and community in mediterranean cultures
such as greece
italy spain portugal are there deeper
skills and ideologies
that cultivate community that are
completely lacking in the us
there's i'm wondering if you have any
what your take on that is yeah like what
we lose
when our social culture is so around
gathering around is shared interest
versus just getting together for meals
and hanging out
kind of am i getting it yeah yeah yeah
well i i suspect i mean i've
i've lived i lived abroad in china for
many years and many of my
friends are europeans and i get the
sense that there's
there's a deeper substratum to
particularly mediterranean cultures
that is like a glue that it's it's
difficult to
name it and i'm wondering if you can and
i and i just feel like it's completely
absent in america
and i'm almost i so i have not had
personal experience living in other
countries
but i was a consultant for this dinner
series
called palabra which is run by a guy who
lived in spain with his family for a few
years
and moved back to new york city and was
just like
what is going on with us socially
because he'd been in spain where you
are having two three four five hour long
meals and these just like languid
conversations with people
and there's no like let me send you a
google cal
invite for an hour long lunch and then i
need to leave
and actually now his meetings with
people
he'll like only meet with people for two
hours or more
and he's like we're gonna have lunch and
we're gonna chill like we're gonna
really
get to know each other and
that's so counter to our culture
and it's really sad like
i have a friend who's who he lived in
amsterdam for a long time and
we we were on a like a retreat thing
together
and he said how much he missed just how
normal it was for people to just spend
the whole day hanging out together
like it wasn't it didn't feel like a big
deal it didn't feel like a big
commitment
to just be like hey man you want to walk
over to my house and we'll just like
do whatever and to get people to do that
in the united states it's like
that that feels intimidating even to me
to be like want to just hang out all day
and i think there is something very
missing of one being able to be okay
without a plan first of all
to be able to
like engage in a conversation for that
long
and to not have this i think the problem
is this anxious
like monster that's hanging out that's
like you should be
doing something you should be productive
like
that's just murdering this joy we get
in being with people for long amounts of
time
and so that that's what i see and it
sounds like that's kind of
been your your experience as well
maybe yeah more or less yeah more or
less thank you
of course all right
uh kevin you're up
hi jillian how's it going i met kevin at
possible
yeah like four years ago how's it going
good to see you
too hey i have a question for you um
so a lot of a lot of your work is like
connecting people with communities where
they have a lot of options right like
new york city you can go
find a community for any little thing
you want and i think
dan's question sort of touched on this
or you sort of touched on this and
your answer to dan's question were like
um
you're all hanging hanging out around
like a mutual interest
um so like i wonder what your thoughts
are on the differences
between like building communities where
people have self-selected to be there
versus um strengthening
a community that you are for lack of a
better term stuck with
like your family or neighbors or maybe
you live in a small town or something
like that
um and if you have any advice that
you've learned in your experiences that
could be applied to
that kind of situation versus hey we all
and especially like um
you said like campgrounded people are
very playful and open and
a lot of sort of you know like the
festival we met up people have a sort of
shared openness and vulnerability and
how would you
sort of bring that environment into
places where people haven't
self-selected around those values
this is a super great question like how
how can you just be with people and
appreciate them
versus having to like always be in
spaces where you know that there's a
certain set of norms that like are the
best
for you um and honestly this is a thing
that's
part of my work right now is like
there's a big reason why i like i said i
have a newsletter that's around a
specific
type of event because i'm i'm such a
sensitive person
that it really means a lot to me to be
in a space where i feel
held and like everyone's on the same
page
and so for me my work is to
like just be curious about anyone
and this has come up a lot with people
asking like i've been with the same
people during covet and i'm
so sick of them like i'm sick of my
family i'm sick of my partner or
whatever
like what do i do and
the biggest learning i've had which
might sound obvious is to just
be genuinely curious about them and
and that you learn new things about
people when you ask them
new questions and so
like an example in my life that ties to
this is
i was in texas over the summer and there
were some people we were hanging out
with
who were like in our pod that would not
have been
like my first choice of friends in new
york city
and i felt a lot of resistance around
that and like a lot of resentment around
that
and realized first of all
these people are definitely picking up
on that that is my attitude towards them
like they probably don't want to be open
and vulnerable with me if i'm like
coming in all judgy about who they are
uh and i i started asking one of the
guys we were in a car ride
about this video game that he loves like
why
it was like this kind of horror video
game like why he loved it so much
and he gave me the most profound
beautiful answer
about how he loves like being able to
step into the lives of different women
in the game different characters
experiencing the world through that way
playing different
teams and i
was just so struck by his answer to this
thing that
i was judging as like a waste of time
and like stupid
and here he was having this gorgeous
experience with it and i just hadn't
opened myself up enough
to to have a connected experience with
him
and so i think just for anyone if you're
like me
and you really love being in spaces with
your people because
you probably grew up in a family where
you didn't feel like they were your
people
you grew up in a high school where you
didn't feel like you had your people
and so now as an adult you're just like
holding
dearly to these spaces where you can
just be you
uh to just bring that curiosity to folks
who aren't like in your
little bubble universe because
it's it's been really fun for me
recently to be talking to people who
have world views that are very different
than mine like i've been really working
to talk to more people who are
republicans who are conservative who are
trump voters
who are way older than me like those are
those are the people i'm working to
bring into my world
so i can practice that of just learning
through curiosity and so that's
that's my offering around that question
it's so good to see you after such a
long
time i know hi yeah thanks the great
answer
thank you um thank you we'll have to
connect later
um um but also yeah
i do have a follow-up to doubleclick to
use a peter term
um yeah you mentioned like you know the
sensitivity of you know you and i sort
of feel the same way i like
being in a space with friends where i
can sort of talk the way i want to talk
and it's difficult to sort of have that
curious mindset especially around
um you know people where family where i
have history with
all sorts of weird things going on right
um
and one one phrase that came to mind um
a friend of mine who's
uh hit one of his phrases he's coined is
more curious
less afraid so i wonder what you think
about
wait my perception is that like there's
some type of fear that
prevents us from being curious
and i'm wondering if that's something
you agree with or what what do you think
is preventing
you or people in general to carry that
disposition of curiosity
i'm like wiggling because i'm so excited
about this question
uh so like context i just finished this
seven
week course on emotional equanimity
in conversations across lines of
difference
like how can you speak to someone who
sees the world very differently than you
and like keep your cool
and stay curious and open and not close
or explode
and a big point the teacher harry
pickens made was
we often don't put ourselves with people
who hold very different world views
because we're afraid of our minds being
changed
like that point blew my mind
like oh maybe part of me unconsciously
is avoiding
talking to people who support trump
talking to people who are
really republican because i might see
something about myself that i'm afraid
of
i might want to shift a little bit and
if i want to do that then who am i
like that's really scary and so
to like the the work is to go into these
conversations knowing like
this person might change the way i see
things
and to not because people sense it if
you're like holding on to your ideology
so tight like i do this when i'm going
into a conversation with the trump voter
i'm like
you're you're stupid and bad
no one's going to be open with me if i'm
coming in with that mindset
like no one's going to want to share
their heart with me if i'm not willing
to
even hear where they're genuinely coming
from
and that's been a big shift for me
in being with people across lines of
difference is realizing like
i'm afraid that's what this is i'm
afraid of this person
uh so how do you deal with that the uh
triggers um
because you know uh across the political
spectrum people are getting triggered by
liberals people getting triggered by
conservatives
um and then they can feel that you know
like a mirror neurons fire like they
feel that
you don't like the person um and so how
do you do that internal sort of like jiu
jitsu moves in order to
not allow that to affect the interaction
yeah
like first of all shout out to harry
pickens he's incredible
um he
really suggested first of all like
there we would always do this exercise
of on the one hand on the other hand
and we would like literally use our
hands uh
to show that like nothing is ever one
thing
and it's such i've been told this is
like a white thing
i don't know how it's true but maybe if
i'm assuming it is of the like
very black or white like it's either
this way or it's this way and there's
nothing in between
uh to realize that like with every bad
thing that happens that there's always
something that's in on the other hand
uh i'm trying to think of an example
when i'm feeling self-conscious
like on the one hand our schooling
system
completely messed up how we talk about
columbus
on the other hand now we're having
really rich conversations about
how we need to redefine how we teach and
like why that's happened in the first
place
like yes this shitty thing's been going
on for forever
and now we have this incredible
opportunity to change the narrative
like something along those lines
so that was one thing uh and we we also
talk about historical paradox
of how oh i know i notice i'm getting
nervous while
i'm sharing this like i want to get it
really right um
but how if you focus on
just the bad in our history
you actually like you aren't in
you aren't in your full truth like
you're not really seeing clearly
or you could be very pollyannaish and
like only look at the beautiful positive
things in our history and to realize
like there's there's good and bad in
everything and to be able to hold both
of those truths and have like the wisdom
to hold both of those truths at the same
time
because like you see in the news
it's very tilted towards like everything
is bad and on fire and exploding and
like you should be screaming your head
off right now
when like there are really gorgeous
things happening
like on the one hand covet is terrifying
and it's made us realize how terrible
our leadership is
on the other hand people are supporting
each other and realizing beautiful
things about how their lives aren't the
way they want them to be
and thinking about community support
uh so these are all kind of mindset
things and in terms of like actual your
physical
being um one big thing is just
training your breath like to be able to
breathe deeply
because if anyone here has anxiety you
know
quick shallow breathing will make our
nervous systems freak out like our
we're not able to think as clearly
uh what harry says is stress makes us
stupid
like the more charged up you are the
less
clearly you are able to think which
totally makes sense and so how can we
train our nervous systems
to be calmer in moments of conflict
and that could look like doing more
breath work meditating more
just having a constant check-in practice
of how deep am i breathing right now
what's going on in my body uh he would
always have us on zoom
just like take breaks to yawn and
stretch because yawning calms her body
down
so like real pretty on whatever but we
were just always just like
stretching on um
so that's some stuff that's some stuff
i'm using all my stoic
willpower to not yawn right now so let's
just
um yeah so yeah you're going on it's
okay
um so we have some good questions uh
let's go with hannah school your
question hannah
hi jillian so i have
a question surrounding friendships
my question is how do you know if
someone is your friend
and i'll contextualize this a little bit
uh i find i'm often in situations
where uh
like a work situation i'm not sure if
someone is being friendly out of
convenience
or because they actually like me so
things like that make me wonder
well i guess if you're okay with me
asking you a question
and if you're not totally fine
but when do you feel like you're being a
friend to someone
[Music]
i think when i hold space for people
to get out whatever they need to get out
yeah that's really beautiful like
holding space for someone
allowing them to share uh
because i think like there is a whole
conversation
online about like our work friends
really real friends
like are they just relationships out of
convenience that sort of thing
and i think it just comes to your own
individual discernment of like
is it okay with me to have someone who
is a friend
in my workplace and we don't hang out
outside of work
like does that feel good uh or
i'm not sure if your question comes from
a place of like
we're talking at work but really what i
would love is to be able to see them
outside of work
and are you comfortable asking for that
are those the norms in your company do
you wish they were different
just like that it's it's so different
person from person
company from company and i have had
really beautiful friendships
in work situations and like
really transformative mentorship
situations as well
and it's um there's a great book by my
friend shasta nelson
called the business of friendship that's
about
friendships at work uh which maybe might
help get clarity on like
what really like what
what your dream friend even really is
and like what
what's lacking what's not
because i mean i feel like
every piece of advice that applies with
romantic relationships
a lot of it applies to friendships as
well if someone's like how do i know
what kind of romantic partner i want
it's like
like think about it like what qualities
in people do you love like what types of
people do you naturally gravitate to
if if you could be friends with any type
of person like
your your own self-limiting like worth
stuff aside who would those people be
how would you feel around them what
would you do and just like have a little
fun
exercise with that um this is just me
getting off at a tangent completely not
connected to your questions so i'll stop
no i like this keep going well just that
like
i feel like anything around worth that
applies with
um like with money with romantic
relationships that same stuff applies
to friendship like i
had shallow
like a little mean friendships when i
was growing up
because i didn't know it but that was
what i thought
i deserved that's what i wanted or
whatever
it wasn't abusive it was just not ideal
um and now that
i i've like really worked on loving
myself more and i've opened my
aperture up to the quality of people
that i want in my life
it's just like all i see is incredible
people in the world like that's how my
world view has shifted but it
takes a crap ton of work
like just as much with friendships as it
does with romantic relationships
and sometimes more because we don't talk
about friendships in that way like it's
not
there's not nearly as many books
published about friendships as there are
about romantic relationships and that's
for good reason
um there's a term called a motto
normativity
which means i feel like this is a word
you all like this
is very simple um but it means like a
culture that
puts romance first that says like
romantic love is the pinnacle of
relationships
a modern normativity i used it in a ton
of time so i can sound very smart
um but it's true that it's like oh my
god when you have a romantic partner
then every like then you've done it and
you're set
in terms of relational life i'm like
that's so not true but that's what our
culture teaches us
this is my long rant hope it was helpful
for you
it's reminding me actually of uh esther
perel
when she's talking about you know uh you
used to have
so many different relationships
throughout your community to support you
and now all of those roles are placed
onto
the one significant other figure in your
life
and it's uh it's an expectation that's
doomed
basically yeah like it's not fair to put
all of that on one person
it's also not fun to put all of that on
one person either
thank you very much of course thank you
for asking hannah
all right uh we have about five minutes
to the hour
are you okay to squeeze in another
question oh please i'm like i'm just
chilling i'm at home
um okay amy you're up
um sorry my camera's off i there's a
storm here
um but i had a question which is let me
just go back to it
um this is just something that's kind of
more of a a
little bit more of a hypothetical
question um
basically since i live in new york city
too and since um
since kobit i have been kind of feeling
a hunger to meet individuals from the
store group in person like it really
bothers me that i mean it's on one here
and an amazing group but on the other
hand that
like not having the physical proximity
of these people
it's like been it's been uh it's been
sad for me and i was wondering if there
could be a um
a shift in the future where people with
similar values
who meet online might be relocating to
better support and align with each other
and i'm wondering if this might be the
next step in the game of social
cohesion and reliance
that's beautiful like i'm hearing you
say
like when people meet each other online
and they really share
values to take that offline and me
in the physical space is that is that it
yeah
like i'm just trying to think of that it
just feels like that we're in such a
time of change
and the idea of values has been so much
on my mind and something i'm hearing a
lot about and i'm just wondering
if this might be the next step in the
future of
social cohesion i mean that's my hope
like my dream for and sorry there's
sirens going off outside very new york
city um
is that people come out of this time
where
i hope people are forced to see how
important coming together is because
we've been forced to feel the pain of
what it's like to not have it
and so after this to realize like what a
gift
if like killed it wasn't a thing right
now
to be able to just have a stoa
coffee hour to have stowa's in person to
have a stowa like someone gets at airbnb
and you all meet up
uh like how gorgeous that is and so
i really hope that people who are
gatherers in the future
get more and more credit for the magic
and the community that they create
and that you all create
i'm seeing some some folks in the chat
who want an nyc gathering and i say you
do it
the museums are open y'all stella art
museum crawl please
maybe maybe one day hannah um cool so
let's uh let's close out here
uh jillian any kind of closing thoughts
or anything uh you'd like to
us to know where we can find you what
you're doing next uh
yeah so i first of all you can find me
my newsletter joylist.nyc
but the way is that i make money
connect people right now i offer courses
uh my last one was called better
boundaries my next one
is going to be called courage and
confidence because that seems to be the
number one thing people
in my audience are struggling with right
now it's going to be with my friend sean
gallanos who runs a company called the
love drive
who is an incredible relationship coach
so like i'm the
friendship self-love person and he's the
romantic
love person and we're gonna be a dream
team
uh and also i do one-on-one coaching for
people who feel
disconnected from themselves from their
community and just want a safe place to
explore that and work through it
you can find all of that on the joylist
website
i also speak and i'm looking for more
opportunities to talk to
teenagers like i recently had an
opportunity to speak to a group of high
schoolers and it was so
fun so if you have any opportunities for
me to speak
to high schoolers like that is my jam
beautiful so i'll include all that on
the the show notes uh
and in a moment i will um close out but
jillian thanks so much for coming to
stowa today
lovely thank you um so a couple of
events uh
coming up we have daniel schmuckenberger
uh coming tonight i think it's what is
it
look at the time right um
was it 7 30 p.m eastern time uh the
digital porch is a part of sensemaker in
residence
four part series and after that on the
same link a rap
unbattles uh it's going to happen with
tyson wagner so rap battles tear people
down
rap on battles we build them up through
compliments and and
building on you know the philosophy that
gets spoken so that should be fun
uh and then you might like this one
jillian uh tomorrow we're launching a
series at the stoa
5 30 p.m eastern time called communitas
club where we ex margaret and i are
going to explore different
conversational modalities like uh
verbal aikido non-violent resistance
circling restorative circles all this
cool stuff we're going to bring in an
expert
and then practice it and then maybe port
in the store and mix them all together
and all that have
modality sex so check that out um
and we have tons of events on the
website uh we have a patreon and our
mailing list if you want to stay
connected
is that being said jillian everyone
thanks so much for coming to stowa today
let's play some uh lonely music